<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>MattersEarthly - articles</title><link href="https://mattersearthly.co/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://mattersearthly.co/feeds/articles.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://mattersearthly.co/</id><updated>2021-01-17T21:55:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>Gamification</title><link href="https://mattersearthly.co/articles/gamification.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-01-17T21:55:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-01-17T21:55:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Michael O</name></author><id>tag:mattersearthly.co,2021-01-17:/articles/gamification.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Gamification grew from a mix of interacting trends and traditions in interaction design and games. Gamification describes those features of an interactive system that aim to motivate and engage end-users through the use of game elements and mechanics. The two common definitions of gamification in academic research are by Deterding et al.&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and Huotari and Hamari&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The former defines gamification as “&lt;em&gt;use of game design elements in non-game contexts&lt;/em&gt;”, whereas the latter defines gamification as a “&lt;em&gt;process of enhancing a service with affordances for gameful experiences in order to support user’s overall value creation&lt;/em&gt;.” The key differences …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Gamification grew from a mix of interacting trends and traditions in interaction design and games. Gamification describes those features of an interactive system that aim to motivate and engage end-users through the use of game elements and mechanics. The two common definitions of gamification in academic research are by Deterding et al.&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and Huotari and Hamari&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The former defines gamification as “&lt;em&gt;use of game design elements in non-game contexts&lt;/em&gt;”, whereas the latter defines gamification as a “&lt;em&gt;process of enhancing a service with affordances for gameful experiences in order to support user’s overall value creation&lt;/em&gt;.” The key differences are Deterding et al.’s&lt;sup id="fnref2:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; definition explains how to operationalise gamification (how to apply) and prioritises the game design elements. Huotari and Hamari&lt;sup id="fnref2:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; is a process description incorporating more than just the system or methods and suggests that the focus should be on the user experience, whatever form the final product might take. Gamification is a process of enriching artefacts with game-design elements in order to positively influence users&amp;#8217;&lt;sup id="fnref3:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup&gt;,&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id="fnref3:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.   &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The levels of game design elements outlined in Deterding et al.&lt;sup id="fnref4:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; are presented in the table&amp;nbsp;below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class="table"&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;th&gt;Level&lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;th&gt;Description&lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;th&gt;Example&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Game interface design elements&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Common, successful interaction design components and design solutions for a known problem in a context, including prototypical implementations&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; Badge, leaderboard, level
      &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Game design patterns and mechanics&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Commonly reoccurring parts of the design of a game that concern gameplay&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Time constraint, limited resources, turns&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Game design principles and heuristics&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Evaluative guidelines to approach a design problem or analyze a given design solution&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Enduring play, clear goals, variety of game styles&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Game models&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Conceptual models of the components of games or game experience&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Mechanics-Dynamics-Aesthetics framework (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;MDA&lt;/span&gt;); challenge, fantasy, curiosity; game design atoms&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Game design methods&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Game design-specific practices and processes&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Playtesting, play-centric design, value conscious game design&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Game conditions presented in previous literature as summarised by Huotari and Hamari&lt;sup id="fnref4:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. &lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Systemic conditions&lt;/strong&gt; refer to how a game is constructed and &lt;strong&gt;experiential conditions&lt;/strong&gt; describe the human involvement in the game. The levels of abstractions outline common features of&amp;nbsp;games.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Level of abstraction&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Systemic conditions&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Experiential conditions&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1st level (common to all games)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Games as systems&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Requirement of player/user voluntary involvement
      &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2nd level (characteristic of games but not necessary in all games)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Conflicting goals
          Rules
          Variable and uncertain outcomes
      &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Hedonic pleasure
          Mastery/achievement
          Relatedness
          Suspense
          Competence
          Flow and Immersion
      &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3rd level (unique to games)&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&amp;#8212;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&amp;#8212;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most common features used in gamified applications–points, badges and leaderboards–are not sufficient in themselves to create a game-like experience. They are in fact only used for interaction and feedback. We should target gamification towards increasing intrinsic motivation generated through three points: autonomy, mastery and purpose. Gamification shouldn’t be reduced to just applying game elements and interactive features, it requires an understanding of users’ needs, social styles, their level of expertise and manner of engagement in the task. User behaviour should be the core driving force for a gamified system. Prioritising elements such as points, badges and leaderboards can undermine the complex series of cognitive, emotional, and social affordances that make games intrinsically motivating and enjoyable to play&lt;sup id="fnref:3"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:3"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The design and adjustment of gamified services is thus a complex task that exceeds applying simple point systems, leaderboards and badges&lt;sup id="fnref:4"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:4"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although primarily concentrated in education/training, sustainability and healthcare/wellness, gamification is widespread across different domains. Interest in gamification has grown because technology is increasingly harnessed for motivating and supporting people toward various individually and collectively beneficial behaviours&lt;sup id="fnref:5"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:5"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Many of the studies on gamification aim to test the effect of the particular features implemented, but rarely do this well. Beyond investigating the effects and benefits, there is still lack of understanding on the predictors of why people use gamified services. An extensive amount of literature is primarily descriptive quantitative studies, which do not offer inferences regarding the data and the effect of the gamification (if any at all). There is perhaps a need for more objective quantitative studies, and qualitative studies that delve into users’ understanding of the topic or the system(s) being investigated. The common criticisms of gamification research in the literature&amp;nbsp;include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The lack of a theoretical framework and&amp;nbsp;constructs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Failure to use validated constructs which hinders the development of the field and the understanding of these gamified&amp;nbsp;elements.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Failure to test the most effective gamification&amp;nbsp;features&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The lack of (appropriate) objective&amp;nbsp;measures/research&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A one-size fits all approach that doesn’t consider individual differences (although research in this area is&amp;nbsp;growing).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deterding, Sebastian, Dan Dixon, Rilla Khaled, and Lennart Nacke. 2011. “From Game Design Elements to Gamefulness: Defining ‘Gamification.’” In Proceedings of the 15th International Academic MindTrek Conference on Envisioning Future Media Environments - MindTrek ’11, 9. Tampere, Finland: &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ACM&lt;/span&gt; Press.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref2:1" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref3:1" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref4:1" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Huotari, Kai, and Juho Hamari. 2017. “A Definition for Gamification: Anchoring Gamification in the Service Marketing Literature.” Electronic Markets 27 (1): 21–31.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref2:2" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref3:2" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref4:2" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cheng, Vanessa Wan Sze, Tracey A Davenport, Daniel Johnson, Kellie Vella, Jo Mitchell, and Ian B Hickie. 2018. “An App That Incorporates Gamification, Mini-Games, and Social Connection to Improve Men’s Mental Health and Well-Being (MindMax): Participatory Design Process.” &lt;span class="caps"&gt;JMIR&lt;/span&gt; Mental Health 5 (4): e11068.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:3" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blohm, Ivo, and Jan Marco Leimeister. 2013. “Gamification: Design of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IT&lt;/span&gt;-Based Enhancing Services for Motivational Support and Behavioral Change.” Business &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; Information Systems Engineering 5 (4): 275–78.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:4" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:5"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hamari, Juho, and Jonna Koivisto. 2015. “Why Do People Use Gamification Services?” International Journal of Information Management 35 (4): 419–31.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:5" title="Jump back to footnote 5 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="articles"></category><category term="gamification"></category><category term="motivation"></category><category term="behaviour"></category></entry><entry><title>Game-based Active Mobility with Augmented Reality</title><link href="https://mattersearthly.co/articles/game-based-active-mobility.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-01-15T21:55:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-01-15T21:55:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Michael O</name></author><id>tag:mattersearthly.co,2021-01-15:/articles/game-based-active-mobility.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;
&lt;span class="bigger"&gt; A study to explore how to encourage active mobility and to test participants&amp;#8217; experience and perceptions of a web-based &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AR&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;application.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the world population living in urban areas continues to grow&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. As the global population shifts to urban areas, there is an increased need for practical solutions to address the physical and mental wellbeing of citizens and to enhance the standard of living in urban environments. Among the problems in urban areas are premature mortality rates caused by physical inactivity and sedentary lifestyles, which lead to chronic diseases. According to World Health Organization (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;WHO&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, physical inactivity …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;
&lt;span class="bigger"&gt; A study to explore how to encourage active mobility and to test participants&amp;#8217; experience and perceptions of a web-based &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AR&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;application.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the world population living in urban areas continues to grow&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. As the global population shifts to urban areas, there is an increased need for practical solutions to address the physical and mental wellbeing of citizens and to enhance the standard of living in urban environments. Among the problems in urban areas are premature mortality rates caused by physical inactivity and sedentary lifestyles, which lead to chronic diseases. According to World Health Organization (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;WHO&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, physical inactivity and sedentary behaviour could partly be attributed to the effects of urbanisation, which has led to detrimental factors such increase in traffic, low air quality and lack of recreational&amp;nbsp;facilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need innovative solutions to address many of the problems we face as society. There has been a steady growth in systems aimed at motivating people to attain their goals by guiding them towards more sustainable behaviours&lt;sup id="fnref:3"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:3"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Digital interventions have transformed the sustainability, healthcare and wellness sectors by enhancing user independence in improving their own wellbeing and overall health. Using technology in these different domains applying techniques such as gamification to start and maintain self-beneficial behaviour is nowadays commonplace&lt;sup id="fnref:4"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:4"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup&gt;,&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id="fnref:5"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:5"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Digital technologies in different modalities are now part of our daily lives and increasingly “co-constitute” our experience of the urban environment&lt;sup id="fnref:6"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:6"&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As part of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ULE&lt;/span&gt; project, we are interested in exploring the role of technology in encouraging active mobility in urban environments. A topic that has received increased attention in recent years. One aim of the project is to investigate how to integrate technology into existing urban environments to encourage physical activity, city exploration, and community awareness. Research shows how the characteristics of urban environments can contribute positively to health by influencing people’s physical activity levels. Related to this, we conducted a pilot study in the Autumn of 2020 to examine the role of augmented reality (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;AR&lt;/span&gt;) in encouraging active mobility by providing an enjoyable and interactive experience while exploring an urban&amp;nbsp;environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We asked participants to download and print instructions for completing the tasks from the events website prior to their participation. And during the event, they were to share photos and videos of themselves doing the distinct challenges with the events’ hashtag and location on social media. We encouraged participants to either walk, cycle or use public transportation to get to the checkpoints that were at 30 different locations. The challenges required participants to navigate from point to point in Oulu, a Finnish city in northern Finland, and its environs using a specially prepared map, which they used to find the checkpoints. The checkpoints had posters with &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AR&lt;/span&gt; tags, which participants needed to scan (Figure&amp;nbsp;1).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="../images/lrp00.png" alt="Study design" class="centerImage"&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;b&gt;Figure 1.&lt;/b&gt; Study design – checkpoints, tag code and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AR&lt;/span&gt; tag form&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once scanned, they displayed a video and a code. The video showed the challenge, and each location had its own letter code, which they marked in the printed document after completing the challenge. The challenges required the use of facilities or the features available at each location, for example, doing mild-to-moderate exercises using outdoor stairs, walking/jogging to the top of a hill and taking a photo of the view, using outdoor gym equipment to exercise and so on. We reviewed log data and questionnaire responses after the event. The log data for the number of times participants accessed the application at each location. Three locations had over a hundred downloads, and there were visitors to all 30 locations (Figure&amp;nbsp;2).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="../images/visits.png" alt="Study design" class="centerImage"&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;b&gt;Figure 2.&lt;/b&gt; Number of downloads at each checkpoint&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, participants&amp;#8217; perceptions of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AR&lt;/span&gt; application and its usability were mostly positive. Some particularly enjoyed how the application revealed the challenges at each location. The pilot study provided a good example of how to integrate gameful experiences with the aid of technology into the physical environment. It served as a basis for future work where we plan to use motivation techniques such as gamification to encourage active mobility, social interaction, and sustainable use of urban&amp;nbsp;resources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;United Nations. (2018). 68% of the world population projected to live in urban areas by 2050. United Nations - Department of Economic and Social Affairs. https://www.un.org/development/desa/en/news/population/2018-revision-of-world-urbanization-prospects.html&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;World Health Organization (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;WHO&lt;/span&gt;). (n.d.). Physical Inactivity: A Global Public Health Problem. https://www.who.int/teams/health-promotion/physical-activity&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chatterjee, S., &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; Price, A. (2009). Healthy Living with Persuasive Technologies: Framework, Issues, and Challenges. Journal of the American Medical Informatics Association, 16(2), 171–178.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:3" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Morford, Z. H., Witts, B. N., Killingsworth, K. J., &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; Alavosius, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;M. P.&lt;/span&gt;(2014). Gamification: The Intersection between Behavior Analysis and Game Design Technologies. The Behavior Analyst, 37(1), 25–40.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:4" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:5"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hamari, J., &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; Koivisto, J. (2015). Why do people use gamification services? International Journal of Information Management, 35(4), 419–431.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:5" title="Jump back to footnote 5 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:6"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Papangelis, K., Saker, M., &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; Jones, C. (2020). Smart Cities at Play: Technology and Emerging forms of playfulness. Behaviour &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; Information Technology, 39(6), 607–609.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:6" title="Jump back to footnote 6 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="articles"></category><category term="active mobility"></category><category term="games"></category><category term="urban environment"></category><category term="augmented reality"></category></entry><entry><title>Good for Hood – Sports in Neighbourly Company</title><link href="https://mattersearthly.co/articles/good-for-hood.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-10-17T21:55:00+03:00</published><updated>2020-10-17T21:55:00+03:00</updated><author><name>Michael O</name></author><id>tag:mattersearthly.co,2020-10-17:/articles/good-for-hood.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Exercise and have fun right outside your home! Well, some might require travelling a short distance, but it beats driving or commuting farther away for hobbies or sports&amp;nbsp;activities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Welcome, &lt;a href="https://lahirahina.fi"&gt;Lähirähinä&lt;/a&gt;! Fun and sports with your next-door neighbour (or&amp;nbsp;almost). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lähirähinä is a voluntary program started by &lt;a href="https://jshercules.com"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;JS&lt;/span&gt; Hercules&lt;/a&gt; football club four years ago. The aim is to equip anyone in neighbourhoods around the city of Oulu with the tools to organise easy and open for all (sporting) activities. Guidance and equipment are available for the organisers of the events if needed. Occasionally, members of professional sports clubs hold demo …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Exercise and have fun right outside your home! Well, some might require travelling a short distance, but it beats driving or commuting farther away for hobbies or sports&amp;nbsp;activities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Welcome, &lt;a href="https://lahirahina.fi"&gt;Lähirähinä&lt;/a&gt;! Fun and sports with your next-door neighbour (or&amp;nbsp;almost). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lähirähinä is a voluntary program started by &lt;a href="https://jshercules.com"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;JS&lt;/span&gt; Hercules&lt;/a&gt; football club four years ago. The aim is to equip anyone in neighbourhoods around the city of Oulu with the tools to organise easy and open for all (sporting) activities. Guidance and equipment are available for the organisers of the events if needed. Occasionally, members of professional sports clubs hold demo sessions and provide information about the activities of their clubs at the&amp;nbsp;events. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Organisers use existing resources (outdoor parks, sports halls, open fields) to encourage participants to be active. Besides being activity-oriented, Lähirähinä is also about fostering a sense of togetherness and creating a community spirit where people often socialise. What our isolated and sedentary lifestyles in urban areas often lacks. Lives in which neighbouring families rarely meet in social contexts outside their children&amp;#8217;s hobbies! And what better place to meet others and socialise than right outside your own yard? As sports bring people together, also those in the margins of society can take part in free events organised in their own&amp;nbsp;neighbourhoods. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The overall goal is to improve the wellbeing of society and to encourage sustainable practices in using the public resources. Lähirähinä aims&amp;nbsp;to: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Increase physical activity among residents in their own&amp;nbsp;neighbourhoods. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Provide possibilities to try different sports sometimes guided by&amp;nbsp;professionals. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reduce transportation of children to&amp;nbsp;hobbies. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Promote children&amp;#8217;s and parents’ joint sporting&amp;nbsp;activities. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Promote community spirit and a sense of&amp;nbsp;togetherness. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improve the use of local sports venues or activity&amp;nbsp;parks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To celebrate the different regional communities that organise sporting events, the first &lt;a href="https://lahirahina.fi/lrp2019/"&gt;Lähirähinäpäivä&lt;/a&gt; was in 2019. A family day when people from different neighbourhoods around Oulu take part in physical activity challenges. The second &lt;a href="https://lahirahina.fi/lrp2020/"&gt;Lähirähinäpäivä 2020&lt;/a&gt; in September this year had the theme, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Fun for the entire family, orienteering around the city with augmented reality!”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; Participants traversed Oulu city and its environs looking for &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AR&lt;/span&gt; tags placed in strategic numbered checkpoints. To take part, participants downloaded a form from the Lähirähinäpäivä &lt;a href="http://lahirahina.fi/rastit2020/"&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;. The form gave instructions for completing the tasks, which required scanning &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AR&lt;/span&gt; tags on posters placed at the checkpoints around the city. The &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AR&lt;/span&gt; tag displayed a video with the task for a specific location and an associated code in the video to note down. Participants were also to post videos/photos as/when they did the tasks using the lrp2020 hashtag on social media. Participants needed to complete 6 or more tasks to have a chance of winning a prize in a draw held later the same day. The feedback from the event was mostly positive, and if not for the weather, it would have been an active day in the city&amp;nbsp;🙂.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The day served as a test case for how to integrate technology into the existing urban environment to encourage physical activity and social interaction. This is one of the key focus areas of the Urban Lifestyle Engineering (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ULE&lt;/span&gt;) &lt;a href="https://mattersearthly.co/projects.html"&gt;project&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ULE&lt;/span&gt; is a concept to create, test, and implement best practices for healthier and sustainable lifestyles. The project investigates how existing environments can develop to improve the wellbeing of its&amp;nbsp;citizens. &lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="articles"></category><category term="physical activity"></category><category term="technology"></category><category term="augmented reality"></category></entry><entry><title>The Challenges of Academic Writing</title><link href="https://mattersearthly.co/articles/academic-writing.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-08-26T21:10:00+03:00</published><updated>2020-08-26T21:10:00+03:00</updated><author><name>Michael O</name></author><id>tag:mattersearthly.co,2020-08-26:/articles/academic-writing.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;
&lt;span class="bigger"&gt;Spend 40% of the time researching, 20% actually writing and 40% editing and&amp;nbsp;rewriting.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometime back, I took part in a webinar about academic writing and the issues that lead to challenges when reporting or documenting research. The webinar was hosted by &lt;a href= "https://www.publicationcoach.com" target="_blank"&gt;Daphney Grant&lt;/a&gt;. The points raised in the webinar are those I have often struggled with in my research and in projects, especially in the initial stages when there is a lack of clarity. A summary of the issues discussed in the&amp;nbsp;webinar. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Failure to budget time effectively. Tell me about&amp;nbsp;it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Editing while writing, which is destructive&amp;nbsp;because …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;
&lt;span class="bigger"&gt;Spend 40% of the time researching, 20% actually writing and 40% editing and&amp;nbsp;rewriting.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometime back, I took part in a webinar about academic writing and the issues that lead to challenges when reporting or documenting research. The webinar was hosted by &lt;a href= "https://www.publicationcoach.com" target="_blank"&gt;Daphney Grant&lt;/a&gt;. The points raised in the webinar are those I have often struggled with in my research and in projects, especially in the initial stages when there is a lack of clarity. A summary of the issues discussed in the&amp;nbsp;webinar. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Failure to budget time effectively. Tell me about&amp;nbsp;it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Editing while writing, which is destructive&amp;nbsp;because:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it is like multitasking (an illusion of&amp;nbsp;work)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it makes writing more uncomfortable (and more&amp;nbsp;difficult)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it makes you a bad editor because you don&amp;#8217;t have enough distance and perspective on your&amp;nbsp;work. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A suggested trick is to write in 3-point type, which is too small to read. If you can&amp;#8217;t read it, you can&amp;#8217;t edit! Also, developing the habit of promissory notes&amp;#8230; writing a note in the document to remind yourself to check a fact later and don&amp;#8217;t stop&amp;nbsp;writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lack of good systems for storing documents… besides using reference managers, saving documents with multiple tags gives you different ways to find articles later and ideas about&amp;nbsp;writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Failure to keep a research diary detailing the history of the research as it unfolds. The diary should not contain any research itself, but records opinions about the research. Keeping a research diary also allows you to maintain a writing habit, a low-risk place to write while doing&amp;nbsp;research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Poor editing skills. Editing should be more specific than just reading the same text repeatedly and trying to make it better. As researchers, we should break the habit of editing while writing and re-reading what we have written right after writing.  &lt;br&gt;
There are two types of editing: &lt;strong&gt;Substantive (developmental) and copyediting (line)&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Substantive editing relates entirely to the &lt;strong&gt;content&lt;/strong&gt;. Does the material make sense, is it logical, is it persuasive, is everything in the right order, missing information,&amp;nbsp;etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Copyediting relates to &lt;strong&gt;rules&lt;/strong&gt;. Checking the spelling, average sentence length, antecedents, grammar,&amp;nbsp;etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two types of editing require different approaches. The best way to do substantive editing is to take a break first (incubating). It is important to address your work with fresh eyes, and your eyes will not be fresh if you have recently read your document many times. Ideally, you should have forgotten about what you wrote, and then you will approach the work in a similar mindset to the&amp;nbsp;readers. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve had the break, review the work while reading it aloud and ask yourself whether it will make sense to the uninitiated reader.
Later, when copyediting use software or a copyeditor to help check for any&amp;nbsp;errors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aspiring to spend way too much time working and end up wasting much of that time. Set small reasonable goals, e.g. writing 200 words a day or for 15 minutes every day.  &lt;br&gt;
Book recommendation: &lt;strong&gt;The Now Habit by Neal Fiore&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An accountability system that is too weak. For want of a nail&amp;#8230; The small daily goals you cannot achieve because of a lack of&amp;nbsp;accountability. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perfectionists tend to procrastinate. Procrastination is about poor impulse control. Perfectionism can be a problem, and we should start forcing ourselves to be less than perfect. For example, by handing in assignments before it feels less than perfect, sharing crappy drafts often&amp;#8230; It is more important to get the work done and on time than to do it perfectly. Perfectionism can hold your work back. &lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Book recommendation:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;The Checklist Manifesto: If you can talk, you can write&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rewriting should take time. If you spend 20% of the time to write, then you should have plenty of time for rewriting&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We should aspire to write crappy first drafts. It should be the goal because if you write something excellent at first, it shows you are spending too much time trying to edit while you are writing and not enough editing after you&amp;#8217;ve had some&amp;nbsp;distance.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="articles"></category><category term="writing"></category><category term="research"></category></entry><entry><title>UK Research Visit</title><link href="https://mattersearthly.co/articles/uk-research-visit.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-12-17T21:10:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-12-17T21:10:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Michael O</name></author><id>tag:mattersearthly.co,2019-12-17:/articles/uk-research-visit.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;From mid-October to mid-November 2019, I was in the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UK&lt;/span&gt; for a research visit. The opportunity to collaborate closely, exchange ideas, learn from another perspective while in a different work environment is always welcome. &lt;a href= "https://kaute.fi/" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;KAUTE&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, The Finnish Science Foundation for Technology and Economics, funded the research visit. While in the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UK&lt;/span&gt;, I worked with  &lt;a href= "https://www.rachelburrows.net" target="_blank"&gt;Dr Rachel Burrows&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Digital Interventions for the Marginalised in&amp;nbsp;Society&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aim of the visit was to investigate the use of digital interventions to address the needs of the marginalised in society, to understand the challenges in designing these interventions and the opportunities they avail.  The …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;From mid-October to mid-November 2019, I was in the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UK&lt;/span&gt; for a research visit. The opportunity to collaborate closely, exchange ideas, learn from another perspective while in a different work environment is always welcome. &lt;a href= "https://kaute.fi/" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;KAUTE&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, The Finnish Science Foundation for Technology and Economics, funded the research visit. While in the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UK&lt;/span&gt;, I worked with  &lt;a href= "https://www.rachelburrows.net" target="_blank"&gt;Dr Rachel Burrows&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Digital Interventions for the Marginalised in&amp;nbsp;Society&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aim of the visit was to investigate the use of digital interventions to address the needs of the marginalised in society, to understand the challenges in designing these interventions and the opportunities they avail.  The marginalised could include asylum seekers, low-income communities, those without access to financial services, those living in rural areas and so on. In the initial plan, we were to focus on homelessness but decided to first review contemporary research on marginalisation before investigating digital interventions for the&amp;nbsp;homeless. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marginalised communities face significant barriers and inequities in entitlement and access to even basic needs. These include limited access to digital content and/or know-how, communication difficulties, lack of social support and other socioeconomic challenges leading to their stigmatisation. This prevents the marginalised from taking part in societal interactions and navigating the complex and ever-changing social system. For these reasons, the marginalised communities represent unique, urgent and poorly understood challenges with the potential for many technological solutions. There needs to be an in-depth understanding of these unique design challenges posed before implementing any digital&amp;nbsp;intervention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the visit, we analysed literature on different marginalised communities to find the common themes from research. Among the key findings from our initial research was the important role of social support. Social support from peers who help to relay important information to those without digital means and from social workers. Social workers who act as mediators and help marginalised communities to find relevant information. Another important finding was the role of policies in amplifying or mitigating the delivery of services. Policymakers should understand the unique challenges of marginalised communities in order not to enact policies detrimental to their wellbeing. Welfare policies and systems can influence the delivery of services; and the individual capacity of a homeless person, for example, could impact their willingness to, and the way they interact with the service systems. This is because the way systems are configured affects the delivery of services and the quality of the service&amp;nbsp;provided.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Th next steps after the visit are to submit for publication the results of our review and to integrate the findings from the review into at least one other study. The review focuses on investigating existing digital approaches to addressing the needs of the homeless and the outcomes of these. The following study will focus on understanding inclusion and user values from systems thinking&amp;nbsp;perspective.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="articles"></category><category term="research"></category><category term="technology"></category><category term="marginalisation"></category></entry><entry><title>Technology, your daily companion and more if only you let it</title><link href="https://mattersearthly.co/articles/technology-your-daily-companion.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-09-12T22:21:00+03:00</published><updated>2019-09-12T22:21:00+03:00</updated><author><name>Michael O</name></author><id>tag:mattersearthly.co,2019-09-12:/articles/technology-your-daily-companion.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Tomorrow, contrary to initial plans, only brought more delays. I had planned to do more but wasn&amp;#8217;t able to for one reason or another. I ended up spending more time on one task than I should&amp;nbsp;have. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, many tasks are behind schedule and the approaching deadline is a bit too soon. If only there was a system to track and remind us of our own plans which we sometimes fail to meet! Sound familiar? A trivial example, perhaps but a pointer to the most basic of problems that technology can help us to address if only it is …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Tomorrow, contrary to initial plans, only brought more delays. I had planned to do more but wasn&amp;#8217;t able to for one reason or another. I ended up spending more time on one task than I should&amp;nbsp;have. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, many tasks are behind schedule and the approaching deadline is a bit too soon. If only there was a system to track and remind us of our own plans which we sometimes fail to meet! Sound familiar? A trivial example, perhaps but a pointer to the most basic of problems that technology can help us to address if only it is designed&amp;nbsp;right. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whenever I am asked about my research, I often get a startled look when I say my research focuses on the design of persuasive systems. At first mention, it always seems like an alien concept plus persuasion and technology in the same sentence does not make for sound reading. At least, until I give an example of the systems, like social media sites, which we frequently use and have come to rely on for more than just regular day-to-day&amp;nbsp;communication. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These systems are inherently persuasive as their main aim is to get us to either share, inform, or learn from one another. They do that by providing interactive and engaging experiences that encourage regular visits. For example, how many times do we feel an urge to check a notification or decide to visit the social sites for a few minutes only to find ourselves still scrolling a while&amp;nbsp;later?  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Persuasive systems design can make our behaviours more&amp;nbsp;sustainable&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Computers were initially meant for simple tasks like calculation, retrieval, and storage of data. Through innovation they have become ubiquitous and embedded in almost everything we do. For example, it is now possible to independently and remotely learn (a new language or subject), monitor our health or wellbeing, become greener and more energy efficient, save money, overcome an addiction, and so&amp;nbsp;forth. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Persuasive systems are interactive systems that motivate change in users without the use of coercion or deception. These are systems developed to enable people to accomplish tasks they either would like to do or already like doing but don&amp;#8217;t have the requisite motivation&amp;nbsp;for. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our lives are now increasingly intertwined with technology. Thus, studying how technology influences our everyday actions and how we can achieve positive and sustainable behaviour change through the use of these technologies is of utmost importance. Furthermore, with the many opportunities technology now avails, it is important to develop appropriate solutions that match users’ needs and this is where persuasive systems design can&amp;nbsp;help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The design of persuasive systems is user-centred, grounded in social psychological and environmental factors, and involves developing systems that meet the users&amp;#8217; primary goals, facilitate interaction, are credible, and provide opportunities for social&amp;nbsp;interaction. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, persuasive systems design is often driven by a rationalist perspective which often assumes that given clear instructions and if people are motivated, they will easily follow all the steps needed to meet their objectives. But research by Dan Ariely and others has shown that this is far from the case. We are &amp;#8220;predictably&amp;nbsp;irrational&amp;#8221;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, among the aims of my research has been to understand the role context plays in users&amp;#8217; decision making. And to translate this understanding into the design of persuasive systems and behaviour change programs that users stick to. As Jodi Forlizzi stated in her keynote address at the persuasive technology 2015 conference, “If we are in the behaviour change area, we need to have a deep understanding of the problem area—users and the contexts they&amp;nbsp;own”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was also posted at &lt;a href= "https://www.oulu.fi/blogs/science-with-arctic-attitude/persuasive-systems" target="_blank"&gt;Oulu University&amp;#8217;s blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="articles"></category><category term="persuasive systems"></category><category term="technology"></category><category term="behaviour"></category></entry><entry><title>Falling Walls Lab</title><link href="https://mattersearthly.co/articles/falling-walls-lab.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-08-16T21:30:00+03:00</published><updated>2018-08-16T21:30:00+03:00</updated><author><name>Michael O</name></author><id>tag:mattersearthly.co,2018-08-16:/articles/falling-walls-lab.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Two years ago, I registered for a pitching event in the week before mid-summer of 2016 in Turku. I arrived in Turku early in the morning, so I had time to review my presentation in peace. The hour spent at the park by the Aurajoki River practicing before the event venue opened helped calm my nerves. It was a calm, bright and warm summer morning with few people outside. The mind could drift away while watching the river flow and listening to&amp;nbsp;birds,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My pitch went well and there were also interesting presentations from other participants. As I travelled over …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Two years ago, I registered for a pitching event in the week before mid-summer of 2016 in Turku. I arrived in Turku early in the morning, so I had time to review my presentation in peace. The hour spent at the park by the Aurajoki River practicing before the event venue opened helped calm my nerves. It was a calm, bright and warm summer morning with few people outside. The mind could drift away while watching the river flow and listening to&amp;nbsp;birds,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My pitch went well and there were also interesting presentations from other participants. As I travelled over 600 km to an event I dread, had to give myself a pat on the back! I gave all the relevant details within the 3-minute time limit of the pitch, which was a welcome surprise as I did not manage this during earlier practice&amp;nbsp;sessions. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our idea was well-received and the societal impact was its strongest point, but it lacked a clear focus. For me, the most important was stepping outside my comfort zone and getting feedback. Just being there pitching was already a minor victory! The presentations of the top three were excellent. Considering the response and overall feedback from the judges and the other contestants, I should continue to develop the idea further. A summary&amp;nbsp;below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Breaking the Walls of Access to&amp;nbsp;Education&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Enhancing education a locality at&amp;nbsp;time!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;   &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Problem&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;#8212; many public schools in Kenya, and especially those in rural areas, do not have access to library facilities. Many students do not have many options to broaden their knowledge beyond what they learn in&amp;nbsp;schools. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Solution/Idea&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;#8212; to develop a set of community-run digital libraries powered by renewable energy for schools in rural and/or remote areas with intermittent power supply. A secondary aim is to integrate a system for transcribing and storing languages within the library. Some indigenous languages are disappearing at a fast rate, and it is important that we document these languages for future&amp;nbsp;generations.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The library being community-run creates a sense of togetherness and ownership and enables the pooling of&amp;nbsp;resources. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Impact&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;#8212; a community that learns together, grows together. The overall impact will be to strengthen community ties by providing opportunities for collective self-development and learning. Opportunities that may not be available to all&amp;nbsp;students.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="articles"></category><category term="pitching"></category><category term="ideas"></category><category term="research"></category><category term="Turku"></category></entry><entry><title>Doctoral Defence</title><link href="https://mattersearthly.co/articles/doctoral-defence.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-05-15T23:05:00+03:00</published><updated>2018-05-15T23:05:00+03:00</updated><author><name>Michael O</name></author><id>tag:mattersearthly.co,2018-05-15:/articles/doctoral-defence.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;During my doctoral studies, I attended a few PhD defences. Sometimes I made notes of the important points/questions raised whenever I attended any defence. Some opponents concentrate on the methodological approach and the rationale for the overall study, whereas others focus on the definition of terms and the practical implications of the research or a bit of both. As our group&amp;#8217;s research focuses on persuasive systems design and behaviour change, the opponent during one of my colleague&amp;#8217;s defence, asked for an actual situation where an application could change behaviour. This was not about one particular system, rather …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;During my doctoral studies, I attended a few PhD defences. Sometimes I made notes of the important points/questions raised whenever I attended any defence. Some opponents concentrate on the methodological approach and the rationale for the overall study, whereas others focus on the definition of terms and the practical implications of the research or a bit of both. As our group&amp;#8217;s research focuses on persuasive systems design and behaviour change, the opponent during one of my colleague&amp;#8217;s defence, asked for an actual situation where an application could change behaviour. This was not about one particular system, rather a broader view of the effectiveness of persuasive/behaviour change support&amp;nbsp;systems.    &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Defences also differ in their format depending on the opponent. Some are like a debate whereas others are more of a conversation. In the former, the opponent tests the pressure points of the candidate and tries to gauge their responses to tough questions. The latter is a more relaxed setting where the opponent engages in a conversation with the candidate to understand their thought process during the doctoral studies and how the thesis process developed. There are also opponents who preview the planned questions and their level of&amp;nbsp;difficulty.    &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some questions/issues that often come up during PhD defences&amp;nbsp;include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why did you engage in this area of&amp;nbsp;research?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What did you hope to achieve from the&amp;nbsp;research?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On what grounds did you decide on whether some works apply to your&amp;nbsp;work?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The overall plan, whether you met initial goals, and the reasoning behind the order of articles (for article-based&amp;nbsp;theses).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What was the toughest part of your&amp;nbsp;work? &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Comments about the inconsistent definition of&amp;nbsp;terms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why the focus on a particular topic and/or&amp;nbsp;context?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Considering whether awareness of the research methodology is part of a researcher’s&amp;nbsp;obligation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Highlighting the gaps in literature that the research questions&amp;nbsp;address. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Research perspective&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
When thinking about the results, does culture, for example, play a role (depending on the type of research and the target population)? Consider the context of the research and how it might apply to different ethnic backgrounds.  &lt;br&gt;
Address the applicability of the research and to which audiences it applies — the key knowledge&amp;nbsp;gap.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summary of the Studies&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
What would have happened if the studies were in reverse order? &lt;br&gt;
What would it have done to the significance of the results and contributions of the work? &lt;br&gt;
What are the most surprising findings from the studies done on [research topic]? In relation to the published work, the overall findings and the&amp;nbsp;implications?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A subjective reflection of my&amp;nbsp;defence&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My doctoral defence was not the greatest of presentations, but I addressed my opponent&amp;#8217;s questions well and we had a pleasant&amp;nbsp;discussion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Considering how the morning of the defence went, it was a bit of relief to get through the presentation without major issues. I tried to rehearse, but I could barely string together two clear sentences and this was while presenting to my partner and brother-in-law! That raised the nervousness scale to a level I did not want a few hours before the major event. Luckily, I got over it quickly and I was relaxed by the time of the&amp;nbsp;defence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The beginning of the presentation was tense, but as with many of my presentations, it got better as it progressed. If only I could present as freely as I write&amp;#8230; often when presenting I struggle to find the right word and end up repeating the same basic terms. Despite these minor issues, the presentation went well and from the audience&amp;#8217;s point of view, there weren&amp;#8217;t any confusing issues. At least one of my friends, who was not familiar with the topic, said they understood the presentation and they could follow the exchange with my opponent, which was a good&amp;nbsp;sign.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond the specifics of particular studies, my opponent also tried to gauge my understanding of the implications, of not only my research but the field of persuasive systems research. There were a few speculative questions in which I had to think of the broader implications of my research and how to adapt the research to different problem situations. This was important as my dissertation did not concentrate on a particular problem domain but focused on how to improve the design and development of persuasive systems by adapting concepts from other scientific fields (e.g., psychology and software engineering) and investigating how persuasive features are implemented in existing&amp;nbsp;systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did not have a proper response to some questions as expected, but this was not the primary aim. Rather, the aim was to test my understanding first, of the implications of the research for practice, and second, of the generalisability of my research&amp;#8217; findings. How could the practices, design principles, etc., outlined in my research apply in different problem domains? Which are the best strategies to choose in these different problem&amp;nbsp;domains? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What the debate did well was to help break down persuasive systems (design) research into easily digestible steps that anyone could understand (I think). We did not use (or there was no need to) explain any ambiguous terms and what I especially liked, was that the opponent did not delve too much into the research method. We spent little time, in contrast to some defences, about the why this over that method type of&amp;nbsp;questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now comes the tough part of how to move beyond/extend the studies and come up with new research directions&amp;nbsp;🙂&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="articles"></category><category term="PhD"></category><category term="research"></category><category term="doctoral defence"></category></entry></feed>